טוב *Tov*. Happy יום ירושלים *Yom Yerushalayim*. Third day of the עומר
*Omer*. Is this around 49? Not going, not going, all right.
Oh man, no.
We pick up on ל"ו *Lamed Vav* עמוד א' *Amud Aleph*, פרק
ג' gimel. *Perek Gimmel*, משנה Mishnah ב' *Mishna Beis* in מידות *Middos*.
All right, we're talking about the structure of the מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbe'ach*.
So we talked about how it was 32 at the base, although
the base was really only covered two and a half, like two
sides and the edges, and that it was 24 by 24 at
the top where the actual space for the fire was. Okay. וקרן
מערבית דרומית *V'keren maaravit dromit* and in the southwest corner. So again,
remember the ramp here, this is our מזבח Mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*, right? The
ramp is at the south and the west is facing the היכל
Heichal, *Heichal*. So the southwest corner is over here. It's, now by
the way, the significance of the southwest corner is that it's פני
המזבח *pnei hamizbe'ach*, it's the face of the מזבח Mizbeach *mizbe'ach* and
it's לפני השם *lifnei Hashem* because it's facing the היכל Heichal, *Heichal*.
So, right, if you see here, right, let's use this or here,
I'll use, right,
I thought I have my big picture here, wait, I got it,
I got it. Anyway,
okay, so the southwest is here. It's פני המזבח *pnei hamizbe'ach* because
it's when you approach the מזבח Mizbeach, *mizbe'ach*, it's the face of
it because you come up the ramp on the south, and it's
in front of the היכל Heichal. *Heichal*, so it's west, so it's
לפני השם *lifnei Hashem*. So that has significance because for a lot
of the various זריקות *zrikos* of the blood, or various things require
the southwest corner because it achieves both of those. Now, so in
this southwest corner, by the way, we had mentioned also just repeat
what we said at the end of the day yesterday, that as
you can see if you see this picture, right, it did not
have a base from in the most of the east and most
of the west, but at the little corner the northeast corner and
the southwest corner it did, but anyway it didn't have a base
here, which means you could not do זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* in
the most of the—what
did I say?—most
of the—I'm sorry, south, excuse me, most of the east and most
of the south it did not have a base, which meant that
you could not do זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* in the southeast corner
because you cannot do זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam* unless it's כנגד היסוד
*keneged hayesod*, unless there's a base underneath it. So the זריקת הדם
*zrikat hadam* and by the normal things that were not חטאת chatat,
*chatas*, you did two זריקות *zrikos* which each זריקה *zrika* was at
a corner which spread on two walls, so two which is four,
and you wound up doing it on the northeast and the southwest
corner because those were the only diagonally opposite corners that had, that
were over a base. Okay. So now in this southwest corner, היו
שני נקבים *hayu shnei nekavim*, there were two holes in the base,
כמין שני חוטמים *k'min shnei chotamim*, like two nostrils, דקים *dakim*, thin,
שהדמים הניתנים על יסוד מערבי yesod maaravi ועל יסוד דרומי yesod dromi,
יורדין בהן *shehadamim hanitanin al yesod maaravi v'al yesod dromi yordin bahen*,
that some bloods you would pour on the western base, those were
the bloods that you took out of the היכל Heichal *Heichal* when
you did a קרבן *korban* that you did the זריקת הדם *zrikat
hadam* on the inside of the היכל Heichal. *Heichal*, which is basically
like the cows and the goat that you did on יום כיפור
*Yom Kippur*, when you had these very special things which were פרים
הנשרפים *parim hanisrafim*, like the cow for when the בית bayis דין
*Beis Din* ruled incorrectly and everybody followed them. So the very few
קרבנות korbanot. *korbanos* that you did the דם *dam* inside of the
היכל Heichal *Heichal*, so you when you exited the היכל Heichal. *Heichal*,
as soon as you came out, you encountered as it were the
west base. So you would pour the blood in the west, on
the west base, but here you would do it in this southwest
corner on the west part of that southwest corner. And then other
the other דם *dam* that you would spill at the base, you'd
spill on the west corner because when you come down from the
מזבח mizbeach *mizbe'ach*, as it were, the corner the side that you
are most immediately facing when you come down from the מזבח mizbeach
*mizbe'ach* is the west, right? You go up on, you go, you
go, I'm sorry, not west, excuse me, the south. Did I say
it right the first time? But I said before when you come
out of the היכל Heichal, *Heichal* you do it on the west
corner, right? Because the side that you are facing, right? If you
come—this is the ramp, right? And this is the היכל Heichal *Heichal*
here, so you come out of the היכל Heichal. *Heichal*, you are
facing the west corner, so you do it on the west part.
Then you come down off of the מזבח mizbeach? *mizbe'ach*, you are
facing the south and you do it on, you are well, okay,
but your back is to it but as it were you're opposite
the south, so you do it here on the south part, on
the south hole of the southwest corner. Okay, so you had these
two holes, one towards the west, one towards the south, and that's
where you would do to pour the blood.
And you do it they're both like on a line, not like
like this, they're both like that.
Okay, even so one was primarily towards the west, so that's fine.
That could be. So fine, so that one way they have that
picture, the one that's still more western was for when you came
out of the היכל Heichal *Heichal* and the one was that was
not as western was when you came was when you did the
finished the זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam*. Also not even if you came
off the ramp, when you did a normal זריקת הדם *zrikat hadam*
you did it on the floor, so you did a זריקה *zrika*
here, right? and then you came around, right, and then you did
the זריקה here, and you were standing right at that corner, okay?
So the hole that was facing more to the west would be
when you came out of the היכל, Heichal and the hole that
was not as much to the west or facing at the south,
you would do... both of them were at the corner, you would
do for the דמים damim from the outer מזבח. mizbe'ach. והיסוד דרומי
יורדים באותן שתי חורין V’hayesod dromi yordim b’otan shtei chorin the דמים
damim that are given on the יסוד מערבי and יסוד דרומי, יורדים,
yordim, they go down through that hole, בהן ומתערבין באמה, bahen u’mit’arvin
b’amah,
and then from there they mix. It's not exactly clear some, according
to some מפרשים, meforshim, as soon as they went through that hole,
they went right onto the floor. Did they go under the floor
or where did they exactly go? Some say, you know, they went
into this little hole. This whole thing was like what, an אמה,
amah, like a foot and a half? So, okay, they went down
that hole. Maybe there was like an opening at the bottom of
the... you know, there was a hole here, right, and there was
an opening here and they went through the hole and out of
the opening and into that, you know, water that was running through,
the channel that was running through and from there ויוצאים לנחל קדרון,
v’yotzim l’nachal Kidron, it went out to the Kidron Valley to the
east. So they had this again, this running water that would go
through that, all this stuff would get, all the liquids and all
the various stuff would get sort of swept in there and then
it would go out to the Kidron Valley.
Where was this running water?
Yeah, they don't have a picture of it. I know. I don't
know exactly where it was. Okay. Now, ג. gimel.
The impression I always got is that there was like a really
deep hole, you know, like...
Yeah, that's how the מפרשים meforshim say anyway. It's clear from other
things that they were like... that they swept things into the... into
this אמה. amah. What? It's hard to sweep... no, not the blood.
There are other things that they would sweep into it, like the
coals... remember that they would... the extra coals that would fall out
when they did קטורת? Ketoret? Okay, ג. למטה ברצפה באותה קרן מקום
היה שם אמה על אמה. Lemata b’ritzpa b’ota keren makom haya sham
amah al amah. So lower down on the floor, in that corner,
there was a place an אמה amah by an אמה. amah. So
remember before we mentioned that they had like a box an אמה
amah by an אמה amah with a... with a... like what do
you call it? With the... right, with the marble top that they
had the rings in? So this was again basically it's like a
manhole cover. So they had an אמה על אמה, amah al amah,
וטבלא של שיש, v’tavla shel shayish, and it had a... a... you
know, a tableau, you know, a square out of marble on top
of this hole. So it was like a manhole cover, okay? Somebody
used to tell me that a classic question that they would ask
on interviews at IBM, which is why are manhole covers round? As
opposed to square, here it's square. Any thoughts on that?
Because people are...
That's what I used to think, that it was more efficient for
people.
They say it's easier to replace a round manhole cover than a
square manhole.
Why, just harder to make them?
No, it's... it's easier to...
right, you can't put a round hole cover on wrong. You see?
And a square one could even fall down, right, because if it's
at the wrong angle? That's probably the real answer. But anyways this
was square. This wasn't round, okay? וטבלא של שיש v’tavla shel shayish
and... okay, וטבעת היתה קבועה בה, v’tabaat hayta kvua ba, just like
the rings, it had a... just like the keys, it had a...
it had a ring on top of it to pick it up
by, שבו יורדים לשית. shebo yordim lashit. Anyway, that's... they would go
through this into the underground caverns. Okay, so they would use... now
this is the... the גמרא Gemara in particular in סוכה Sukkah discusses
how when they would pour stuff in the holes at the top
here, right, at the top of the מזבח, mizbe'ach. they would pour
the wine and the water, it would go down into the שית,
shit, which was either this deep underground cavern or the more simple
explanation was it was a hollow inside the מזבח mizbe'ach. where the
wine and the water would go. So here they're saying that the
access to those caverns would be with this little manhole cover over
there with the corner of the base. They pick it up and
they go in, which makes sense because they're pouring it over here
anyway. And they would empty it out? Yeah, they'd clean it out.
They'd clean out those... that cavern from all the congealed wine. Now
here it sounds like also blood got congealed, which is a little
funny because it just said that the blood went to the אמה.
amah. So maybe... so they say, well, maybe it means on its
way to the אמה amah somehow it passed through a section of
this and it got congealed and they still had to clean out
that artery, excuse the pun. Anyway, וטבעת... v’tabaat... okay, יורדים לשית ומנקין
אותו, yordim lashit u’menakin oto, they would clean it out. So from
this context it sounds like they would clean it out from the
blood, but often you hear about the שית shit much more in
the context of the what do you call it, of the wine
and the oil and the water for סוכות Sukkot which is poured
up here at the top.
Where was the נחל קדרון? Nachal Kidron?
Yeah, that's what Michael asked. I don't know. It's always mentioned that
there is...
All the way?
Oh, well, the Kidron Valley was right outside. I mean, that was
the picture I gave you.
The Kidron Valley was... Yeah, this... the water, the אמה amah that
went into it, yeah, it doesn't... it never tells like... it seems
like it was running through the מזבח, mizbe'ach but you never describe
where.
Didn't he say the water flows... Didn't we have that?
Yes, yes, they mentioned it a couple of times and they would
sweep, right. Oh, that? Oh, yeah, that was a prophecy for the
future. Yes, that truth...
it wasn't then.
Right, correct. It was some small, I imagine, like something, you know,
that was like a small little... what...
I'm at a loss for a word today, but channel, like, you
know, but very narrow or something, whatever, something that ran
under. All right, so it says, so let's take a look. Okay.
ומינקינה שבצד הכבש. Uminakina shebetzad hakevesh.
והכבש היה לדרומו, Vehakevesh haya lidromo, we've been talking about that, the
ramp was to the south. ל"ב, Lamid bet, was 32 amot long,
like the base of it was 32 amot. ועל רוחב ט"ז, Ve'al
rochav tet zayin,
and the width was 16, okay? So the whole מזבח mizbe'ach. at
the top, so if you think about it, the מזבח mizbe'ach. at
the base was 32. The width of this was 16. So if
we're opposite the base, it had 8 amot on each side, right?
By the time it got to the top, but if you remember
this was 32, then this was 30, then this was 28, and
then you have the horns or whatever, but when it got here
towards the horns, right, it was this was
it was extending 16, so this was 28, so it was only
what,
six on each side?
Six on each side, right, exactly.
Now the other, so now also, by the way, Charlie can tell
us the angle here because he can just do a sine or
cosine or whatever. Because it's 32 at the base, but it goes
up 10 amot. So if you've got a triangle that's 32 by
10, it's a right angle, right? So what is that? That opposite
over adjacent, tangent.
Yeah, it's not a very steep
tangent of of 30 not opposite, it's
tangent, right,
not opposite over yeah, opposite over over adjacent.
10 over 32. Anyway, arctangent of 10 over 32.
Yeah, you'll let us know what the angle is. But it's got,
I think it's a pretty it's a pretty reasonable one, so because
you have to go up and down it a lot. Okay, okay,
anyway, so that was the ramp. ורבובה הייתה לו במערבו, Urevuva hayeta
lo bama'aravo, and there was a little like hole or box or
carved out section in the west, ששם היו נותנים פסולי חטאת העוף.
Shesham hayu notnim psulei chatat ha'of. There they would put the פסולי
חטאת העוף, psulei chatat ha'of, they'd put them there till it got
פסול בלינה pasul belina and then they would throw it out. Now
I must tell you, I don't exactly get why the פסולי חטאת
העוף psulei chatat ha'of more than anything else went there. Now if
it was if by פסולי חטאת העוף psulei chatat ha'of they actually
mean חטאת העוף על הספק, chatat ha'of al hasafek, that's a different
story. If you remember, we talked a lot about that about let's
say, you know, that if if somebody has to become טהור tahor
and they have to bring a חטאת העוף chatat ha'of but they
don't know if they have to, so how are you allowed to
bring a חטאת, you can't bring a חטאת בספק, chatat besafek, it's
חולין בעזרה. chullin ba'azarah. But we have a special we we we
have like a special tradition that you can bring a חטאת העוף
על הספק, chatat ha'of al hasafek, very important of course by a
יולדת yoledet because very often you have cases with miscarriage, you don't
really know if you're חייב chayav a חטאת העוף, chatat ha'of, how
would you become טהור, tahor, you bring a חטאת העוף על ספק.
chatat ha'of al safek. So then what do you do? Then you
wait till it becomes פסול, pasul, you can't eat it, you can't
throw it out, you burn it, you wait till it becomes פסול,
pasul, a day, and then you burn it. So maybe it really
here when it says פסולי חטאת העוף psulei chatat ha'of it really
means ספק safek and that would explain why there's a high incident
of them and then you needed to store them in a place,
you couldn't mistreat them until they become they they became לינה lina
and this is where you'd put it, there'd be a special somehow
carved out place in the מזבח? mizbe'ach. No, the ramp, on the
side of the ramp, either in the it sounds like in the
ramp, you know, hole in the ramp itself that they would just
stuff stuff in until it became פסול. pasul. Charlie, what do you
have for us?
A stone ramp.
A stone ramp, so wait, I didn't see where
16 again, that it was 16 wide? What? Does it did it
16 wide for a reason?
16 wide, no, I don't know, because you don't want to do
the whole length, I mean who knows? I mean whatever, aesthetically or
I don't know. I mean also you needed access to the corners,
I don't know why.
Okay, it could have you still had more room to make it
wider if you wanted to.
If you wanted to, yeah. I mean but this was the way
it was.
Okay, you're saying in the side like of the ramp there was
this hollowed out part? Yeah. Not a part, like it basically they
just there's no wood there. I mean I didn't I wouldn't have
thought it was like one big full piece of wood, you don't
need it like you know full wood even on the bottom. I
would have thought it was just sort of like a frame, you
know what I mean? Like maybe. Like here and then this and
then just a slab of wood here, a slab of wood over
here. What do you say? I mean it wasn't all full of
like one big chunk like your doorstopper, do you think it was
like?
Sure, it's gotta support everybody's weight going up and down it. I
never heard I I I I mean I hear what you're saying,
never heard anybody ever suggest that, I've always assumed that it was
a complete solid block of of stone.
No.
Yeah. Oh it was stone? No.
No, it was stone, it was stone, the whole thing was stone.
Yeah. Oh.
The this hollowed and so you just like stuffed it in there
and like they let it decompose or something?
Yeah. I mean well you let it wait a day till it
was פסול בלינה. pasul belina.
Oh, then you burned it. Yeah. Okay. 17.35 degrees.
Okay, that's a very that's a very reasonable gentle slope, right. Okay.
אבני הכבש ואבני המזבח. Avnei hakevesh ve'avnei hamizbeach.
Now it gets to a an interesting question everybody always wants to
know about how it was constructed and about not using iron and
not carving them.
So we had this in Middot,
we had it in Tamid in
the in the Middot.
Yeah, yeah, so right. Okay, that's true. So we haven't yet. That
was a while ago. אבני הכבש ואבני המזבח, Avnei hakevesh ve'avnei hamizbeach,
whether it's the stones used for the ramp or the stones used
for
the altar, מבקעת בית כרם, Mibik'at Beit Kerem, they would get them.
I have no idea. וחופר למטה מהבתולה v'chofer lemata mehabetula
and you dug the stones from under the virgin earth. You wanted
it from, you know, places that had never been dug. ומביא משם
אבנים שלמות u'mevi misham avanim shlemot
you would bring full stones שלא הונף עליהם ברזל shelo hunaf aleihem
barzel that had not, right, because the תורה Torah says אבנים שלמות
תבנה את מזבח השם אלקיך. avanim shlemot tivneh et mizbe'ach Hashem Elokecha.
What is it? There's two פסוקים. pesukim. אבנים שלמות תבנה את מזבח
השם אלקיך. avanim shlemot tivneh et mizbe'ach Hashem Elokecha. Come on, Michael,
help me out.
I always think, you know, there's two פסוקים.
pesukim. Well, there's two פסוקים, pesukim, right. One is לא תבנה אתהן
גזית כי חרבך הנפת עליה ותחללה lo tivneh atehen gazit ki charbecha
hunafta aleha vatachalaleha and the other is אבנים שלמות תבנה. avanim shlemot
tivneh. So there's both an obligation to have whole stones and whole
stones that had not had metal passed over them. Okay, and that
actually is, you would say well just say whole, obviously that includes
the metal case, because if you carve them with metal they're not
whole. But what you're about to see in the משנה Mishnah. that
no, you could, because you have both prohibitions or both requirements, if
metal even touches them, even if they remain whole, לא תניף עליהם
ברזל, lo tanif aleihem barzel, even if metal is waved over them,
that invalidates them even if they remain whole. So they have both
requirements, whole and never touched metal. Okay, and what about the whole
thing that actually technically ברזל barzel here is iron, yes.
But didn't we, listen to me because because the עזרה azarah was
a little bit different, didn't we say that that was only a
problem if you did it in the עזרה, azarah, whereas if we
did it outside?
So let me talk about that. That was about an עזרה azarah
question. This is about the מזבח. mizbe'ach So I'll address that in
a minute. Let's read the משנה. Mishna Okay, so it has to
be whole stones that had never had any iron waved over them.
שהברזל פוסל בנגיעה shehabarzel posel b'negi'ah because the,
because iron invalidates even by touch, והפגימה בכל דבר v'hapgima b'chol davar
and if it's missing a, if it's chipped, בכל דבר, b'chol davar,
even if anything caused it to chip. So either touched by iron
or if chipped, even the tiniest chip.
And what am I חופר chofer with? What? And what am I
חופר chofer with? If I use my metal shovel, I'm going to
be, you know, what, then I'm מניף עליהם ברזל menif aleihem barzel
aren't I?
No, it has to touch the stone. Oh, you mean how do
you get it out?
How do you get it out without digging and you're digging with
a metal shovel?
It has to touch it. So I assume that if it's surrounded
by dirt, it wouldn't be an issue. But you're saying how do
you not accidentally touch it? Yeah.
I wonder though
if it's only ברזל barzel because it specifically mentions here ברזל. barzel.
As opposed to other
metals?
Like you'd use a gold shovel or something?
Artscroll Artscroll is saying they were quarried with wood. But it doesn't
make any sense that they
would, if they used wood. But you can't, you can't use wood
to chop up stones.
Yeah, but they didn't chop.
They didn't chop them, they had to dig them out of the
ground. Right, so you use a wood shovel. Yeah, the רש״י Rashi
says וחופרין בקרדומות עץ. v'chofrin b'kardumot etz. There you go. The wood,
yeah. I don't know how good you get into virgin earth with
wood shovels. I mean, maybe it's some very, very hard wood, I
don't know. I don't know. I mean, we're going to see in
a minute if it touches through a חציצה, chatzitza, it's not a
problem. But the question you're asking is, well, maybe they just did
that. Maybe they just wrapped the shovels with a type of a
cloth.
You could do
that, wrap a metal shovel with a cloth so that it never
directly touches the stone.
Once you've lost like your, you know, maneuverability.
It's a good question. I don't know. I also don't know if
it's maybe it's limited to ברזל barzel and specifically mentions here ברזל.
barzel.
So yeah, let's keep on reading. It's a very good question.
They couldn't shape them, right?
They couldn't shape them. So what they're going to find out they
did is they used, they basically did, no, they basically made all
of this, as Michael said before, out of a mold and they
made it out of a type of like of a cement. They
didn't really make it out of big stones. They made it out
of a lot of tiny little stones held together by like a
plaster and a
cement.
That wasn't made of stone then.
Right, I mean it was made of stone but lots of little
stones held together by a glue essentially and not by like big
blocks of stone that we tend to think of. It's the only
way you're going to get uncarved stones
and shape the cement.
Exactly. Exactly, but that also explains how you'd get a perfect shape
that way. Well, you could do it by carving, but they didn't
carve.
Exactly, but we can see Herodion stones.
Ah, but that's not the מזבח.
mizbe'ach No, it's not.
So
let's talk about that in a minute. So here, it's a very
good question how they would dig it out of the mountain. But
like I said, maybe it's only ברזל barzel and maybe they put
something around the
shovel. Anyway, let's, נפגמה אחת מהן. nifgema achat mehen. Now if one
of the stones got
chipped, היא פסולה וכולן כשרות. hi psula v'chulan ksheirot. It doesn't invalidate
the whole מזבח. mizbe'ach It's that one is invalid, so you remove
that stone and you replace it, but it's not like the
whole מזבח mizbe'ach is invalid. ומלבנין אותן פעמיים בשנה. u'malbinin otan pa'amayim
bashana. And you would whiten it, which they basically mean you would
replaster it, plaster over
it, okay. Twice a year? Yeah. I heard some of them for,
you could mean you paint it, but the מפרשים mefarshim say it
means plaster, you use a fresh coat of
plaster. פעמיים בשנה pa'amayim bashana twice in the year. אחד בפסח ואחד
בחג. echad b'Pesach v'echad b'Chag. Once before each of the major רגלים
regalim because that's when... everybody is going to be there, so you
make it look nice right before that. Once before פסח *Pesach*, once
before סוכות Succot, *Succos*. וכל ההיכל *vechol ha’heichal* and the entire היכל
Heichal. *heichal*, which some say doesn't even limit it to the היכל
Heichal. *heichal*, but really means the entire בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, פעם
אחת *pa’am
achas*, you did it once in a year בערב פסח *b’erev Pesach*,
right before
Pesach, because that’s—even though people are supposed to be up for all
the רגלים regalim, *regalim*, the biggest turnout is going to be Pesach.
So let me ask you a quick, you know, practical question on
this.
Let me let me finish. Let me just ask the question. רבי
אומר *Rebbi omer*, כל ערב שבת *kol erev Shabbos* מלבינו אותן *malbinoson*,
maybe it’s true they wouldn’t whiten it in the sense that I
said of replastering it only twice a year, but on every ערב
שבת *erev Shabbos* they would clean it, they would whiten it במפה
*b’mappa*, they’d at least use some type of a rag to clean
it, you know, even if they’re not going to replaster it, מפני
הדמים *mipnei hadamim*, because it got all bloody all week. So you
want to clean that out at least once a week. Now, you’re
not disagreeing? No, right, but he’s adding another type of cleaning they
did. לא היה סדו *lo haya sado* בחפיס של ברזל *bechafis shel
barzel*, they would not apply the plaster—and this is why the assumption
is that before when it says whiten it means by plaster—they would
not apply the plaster with an iron applicator, שמא יגע ויפסל *shema
yigga v’yifsal*, because the applicator might touch the actual stone, the actual
מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbeach* and invalidate it, right? Although the plaster is between
the applicator and the actual מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbeach*, but you know, you
can’t always be so careful and you might actually touch it and
invalidate it. And now it ends with a nice midrashic point: שהברזל
נברא לקצר ימיו של אדם *shehabarzel nivra l’katzer yamav shel adam*, because
iron was created to shorten people’s lives, it’s used as a for
weapons of war; והמזבח נברא להאריך ימיו של אדם *v’hamizbeach nivra l’haarich
yamav shel adam*, and the altar is to extend people’s lives through
atonement; אינו בדין שיניף המקצר על המאריך *eino badin sheyanif ham’katzer al
ham’aarich*, it’s not appropriate that the shortener will be waved over the
one that is there to lengthen, which is a nice explanation for
why—why this invalidates and also maybe to point out why even if
it just touches, even without actually chipping away. Now, as you’ll notice,
this is only stated by the מזבח mizbe'ach? *mizbeach*. It is not
stated by the other stones. So there is a possibility and some
say that actually the other stones did not have this prohibition at
all. However, the פסוקים *pesukim*, right, by שלמה *Shlomo*, whatever, says that
no כלי ברזל *kli barzel* was heard, you know, in the whole
בית השם *Beis Hashem*, whatever, sounds like it’s more global. And that
leads to a big problem, which is so how did they get
the stones that they needed, you know, for everything? So there’s גמרות
*Gemaras* about the שמיר *Shamir* that was used to—you know, with some
type of acid to cut it, or the best explanation was, or
the—I mean, most straightforward one is based on that פסוק pasuk *pasuk*
that by שלמה *Shlomo* wasn’t heard on the הר הבית *Har Habayis*,
which is to say you could carve it outside of הר הבית
*Har Habayis* and then bring it to הר הבית *Har Habayis*. But
that only said by
the non-מזבח mizbe'ach, *mizbeach* stones because that’s where already it’s an extension
from the פסוק *pasuk*. The פסוק *pasuk* only speaks about the מזבח
mizbe'ach, *mizbeach*. When it comes to the מזבח mizbe'ach *mizbeach*, nobody says
you can carve it elsewhere. There it’s absolute you cannot use anything
that’s iron, you cannot have a chip, it has to be שלמות
*shleimos*, and therefore we have to explain here that they essentially made
it by a type of a plaster. Again, the question about how
did they dig it out of the ground, you know, I don’t
know. Maybe—maybe—maybe the first dig to break the virgin earth they did
with metal and then afterwards they used the wood? I don't know.
Those are really good questions.
My question is, I mean, if מזבח Mizbe'ach *mizbeach* had to—unless this
is only when they
initially built it—it had to be 32 by 32, but if you’re
adding a coat of plaster year after year and this בית המקדש
*Beis Hamikdash* was around for hundreds of years, right, then this thing
is going to get a lot bigger, right?
That’s an interesting question. Maybe—maybe you like scrape before you replastered, like
right before you paint, you first have to scrape? I don’t know.
That’s an interesting point. Yes.
But then what do you—yeah,
I understand. Yeah. Lime plaster has been used for 4,000 years. Aha.
I’m very surprised because I always thought of lime as being something
that washes away with water, but apparently they figured out a way
to make it dry for a long time. So they didn’t need
to—they probably didn’t need to do very much, probably just smooth it
out a little bit.
As
opposed to replastering, you meaning? As opposed to—yeah.
Well,
but this is just because it was dirty. But, you know what
I mean? Like, you know, they wanted the—blood I’m sure got all
over.
So whitewash is lime. So it’d be like whitewashing it.
Aha. But that would be very thin, it would be a very
thin layer
to make it white again.
Okay. That makes sense.
They didn’t wash the blood off, they just left it there?
Well,
according to רבי *Rebbi*, when he says he wiped it down with
rags, I assume they used water with the rags, right? I mean,
don’t get dry blood off with just rags, so I assume he—and
lime is also a disinfectant.
Mm, interesting. So, you know, so probably even as well as you
wipe it, it’s still going to, you know, stain a little bit,
that’s why—right.
Okay. Now we get to a part that we talked about before
in תמיד Tamid, *Tamid*. הטבעות היו לצפונה של מזבח Mizbe'ach, *hata’ba’os hayu
l’tzafona shel mizbeach*, there were the rings here to the north of
the מזבח Mizbeach. *mizbeach*, right? Because the קדשי קדשים kodshei kodashim. *kodshei
kodashim* have to be שחוט *shachut* in the north, so most of
the שחיטה *shechita* was here. So the whole setup for שחיטה *shechita*
and flaying was here in the north. So it was here in
the north of the מזבח mizbe'ach. *mizbeach*. שש סדרים של ארבע ארבע
*sheish sdarim shel arba arba*, either they were six rows of four
each row, ויש אומרים ארבע של שש שש *v’yeish omrim arba shel
sheish sheish*, or four rows of six in a row. Okay, either
way it was a 6 by 4, just a question length-wise or
width-wise. שעליהם שוחטין את הקדשים *she’aleihem shochtin es hakodashim*. That's where you
would do the שחיטה of the קרבנות. Again, there were some that
didn't have to be in the north, but the whole setup was
in the north because some had to be in the north, all
the
קדשי קדשים. בית המטבחיים היה לצפונו Beit hamitbachayim haya litzfono of the
מזבח. Now also the literally slaughterhouse was to the north, but apparently
what they're calling the בית המטבחיים Beit hamitbachayim is not the place
with the rings. By the way, the rings according to most were
like half rings that they would stick the neck of the animal
through it and like, you know, put the other half, you know,
sort of like a handcuff, a half of a handcuff or whatever,
you know, put the other half in the ground. According to the
רמב"ם, Rambam, they stuck the legs of the animal in it. That's
what the רמב"ם Rambam calls the עקידה akeida that they did with
the animals. Anyway, but after they שחטed shecht them in these rings,
then each משמר mishmar had its own ring, they would move over
further to the north and there where they would have tables and
stands and that's where they would do the flaying and the dismemberment
and deboweling and all of that. Disemboweling I guess. Anyway. That was
custom-made, right?
The rings were probably made of brass.
Yeah, I assume, right.
Okay, so that was called the בית המטבחיים Beit hamitbachayim where they
did actually the flaying and the
dismemberment. היה לצפונו של מזבח, Haya litzfono shel mizbe'ach, that was also
to the north. ועליו ח' עמודים ננסים, Ve'alav chet amudim nannasim, they
had there nine short
pillars. Eight? Why'd I say nine? Eight short pillars. ורביעין של ארז
על גביהם, Verivi'im shel erez al gabeihem, and they had cedar, these
sort of frames on top of
them. ואנקליאות של ברזל היו קבועים בהם, Ve'ankleyot shel barzel hayu kevu'im
bahem, and they had iron hooks in these
frames. ג' סדרים היו לכל אחד ואחד, Gimmel sdarim hayu lechol echad
ve'echad, and there were three rows of each of these hooks. Some
say the reason for the three rows were for the three different
types of animals: cows, goats, and sheep, that you could have different
heights for each one because you have to stretch out the animal
on the entire frame.
So obviously you would hang the animal by the hooks. As you
remember when we discussed this in תמיד, Tamid. you would hang it
by the feet, it would be hung upside
down. שבהם תולים ומפשיטים. Shebahem tolin umafshitin.
All animals were hung upside down?
Apparently, I mean that was the more convenient way to do it.
I assume it didn't matter.
I think it'd be very hard to get like this big cow.
I don't know. שבהם תולים ומפשיטים על שולחנות של שיש, Shebahem tolin
umafshitin al shulchanot shel shayish, with them you would suspend and
flay on the marble tables. The tables were marble so that it
would not spoil, right, so it would keep it cold. שבין העמודים
Shebein ha'amudim between these stands. So you'd have a stand maybe and
then you would have the table. The table is where you'd actually
do your work. Presumably the stand you would take it, you would
get it arranged on the frame, it was on a low height,
to help, I guess, to be, you know, like easy access, to
be manipulated and then once you got it on the frame, I
imagine you took it from the frame to the table and now
you could actually flay it and do the work. Okay.
Three rows?
No, here there are four by six. Right. It just said eight,
it didn't say how many rows. Yeah. Okay. So by each table
you would have this frame, this stand with the frame that you
would set it up and then you'd move it to the table
to do the flaying. Now הכיור. hakiyor. Okay, so that's the מזבח.
And you see what we're doing is we're moving from out inward,
right? We did the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim, then we did the
עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, 11 אמות, amot, then we did the עזרת
כהנים. Ezrat Kohanim. There were these steps and the platform. You'd have
to walk up to get to the עזרת כהנים, Ezrat Kohanim, that
would be the דוכן duchen where the לויים Levi'im would stand. By
the way, I could not find anybody, I'm going to keep on
searching, you know, that said that because we had one thing that
said the לויים Levi'im stood on the דוכן duchen to do the
שירה shira and then we had this whole other discussion of them
in the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim with the musical instruments. So all
the מפרשים mefarshim I've seen say that that was only for סוכות,
but it's funny the way it really emphasized that. But anyway, so
you walk up from the עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael to the עזרת
כהנים. Ezrat Kohanim. That's where the לויים Levi'im stand to do their
דוכן. duchen. Then there's 11 אמות amot also for the עזרת כהנים.
Ezrat Kohanim. Then you have the מזבח. We've now dealt with the
מזבח space. And now we're moving behind the מזבח between the מזבח
and the and the אולם. ulam. בין האולם למזבח Bein ha'ulam lamizbe'ach
which has a higher level of קדושה kedusha as we mentioned the
other day. So now in that space
הכיור היה בין האולם למזבח. hakiyor haya bein ha'ulam lamizbe'ach. So the
laver, you know, the place, this big thing that had the water
that they would wash their hands and feet, was standing between the
אולם ulam and the
מזבח ומשוך כלפי הדרום. umashuch klapei hadarom. It wasn't centered, it was
towards the south. Right, it was towards the, you know, in the
same direction where the, where the, what do you call it, where
the ramp was. So if you right, if you look at this
picture, right, so right, 11 אמות amot here, 11 אמות amot עזרת
כהנים, Ezrat Kohanim, here's the דוכן duchen for the לויים, Levi'im, here's
the בית המטבחיים, Beit hamitbachayim, and now here it's between the אולם
ulam and the מזבח but it is towards the south.
Okay, בין אולם למזבח כ"ב אמות. bein ulam lamizbe'ach chaf bet amot.
Now that space was 22 אמות. amot. Double the space of the
עזרה, ezra, right, it's the combination of the width of the עזרת
כהנים Ezrat Kohanim and the עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael. Then you have
the מזבח and its width. And then you have a similar 22
אמות amot to get to...
starting from the back of the מזבח?
I believe it's from right, the edge of the מזבח, the south
edge of the מזבח, the west edge of the מזבח of
oh wait, no, but how long was it from here to here?
Oh, we knew that.
But that's 32 אמות. amot. Right. So you have 22, 32, 22.
You'll have to figure out if the numbers work. But that's I
believe what we're just
saying. י"ב מעלות היו שם. Yod bet ma'alot hayu sham. Now you
have to go up, you went up steps from the עזרת ישראל
Ezrat Yisrael to the עזרת כהנים. Ezrat Kohanim. Now you have to
go up steps from the עזרה. ezra. כהנים Kohanim to the אולם,
Ulam, okay, that you're going into actually the היכל, Heichal, and there
were twelve steps. Now, what was the height of these steps? So
there's a whole question how to read this, but anyway, I'll read
it the way the
ברטנורא Bartenura reads this. רום מעלה חצי אמה rom ma'alah chatzi amah
so
ושלוחה אמה. v'shilucha amah. So it says like this, the height of
a step was a חצי אמה chatzi amah high, and then שלוחה
shilucha which is like the width, the inset, you go in before
you get to the next step was an אמה. amah. Then, okay,
that's step number one. Then אמה, אמה, amah amah so another אמה
amah, in, another אמה amah, in, so steps two and three were
an אמה amah by an אמה. amah And then ורובד, v'rovad, and
then there was like a more of a platform step, so it
was
ורובד ג' אמות, v'rovad gimel amot, which was three אמות. amot. According
to this what you had was, actually this picture shows it, one,
one, one, one, one, one and this was step one, two, three
and then three אמות, amot, right, is this
what it's called, okay, that's step number four.
Alright, now, how far have we gone so far?
One, two, three, six. There's six אמות amot so far in four
steps. Okay, see what
I'm drawing?
Yes? Okay. Now, there's מחלוקת machloket how to read this. I'm going
to read it the way that I think makes more sense. Okay,
where were we?
Okay, ורובד ג' אמה. v'rovad gimel amah. Now אמה, ורובד ג'. אמה
amah v'rovad gimel amah, אמה ורובד ג'. amah v'rovad gimel. Then another
אמה אמה ורובד ג', amah amah v'rovad gimel.
which is so you've got
one, one, I'll do it a little shorter, one, one,
anyway, and then three. This is steps five, six, and seven and
now we have another five אמות. amot.
Okay, because you're going to see the whole steps are going to
be very long. Okay, which is going to really fill up most
of the space. Alright, and we only have seven steps out of
twelve and we're already eleven אמות amot long.
Okay, and then it says
אמה amah ורובד ג' v'rovad gimel. אמה, אמה ורובד ג'. amah amah
v'rovad gimel, והעליונה אמה אמה ורובד ד'. v'ha'elyonah amah amah v'rovad daled.
And the last one kept on going אמה אמה amah amah, until
you got to the fourth.
So this way to read it is, I'll just continue it here,
we have eight, of course we have אמה amah. אמה, amah, eight,
nine, ten, eleven,
and then finally it was a four, right?
I'm not sure.
So, right, they're going in אמה אמה אמה, amah amah amah, שלוחה
שלוחה shilucha shilucha to the left. So
this is one, two, three, four, eight more אמה. amah. So according
to this you've got, did I do that right? One, two, three,
four, eight. That was one, two, three, six, seven, eight, eleven, yeah.
Anyway that's nineteen אמות amot according to
this.
So this way basically the whole thing was twenty-two אמות amot wide
and the steps were already were nineteen אמות. amot. Now that's the
way I read it, some read it that the steps were twenty-one
אמות, amot, so you only have like one three אמה. amah. Alright,
the רמב"ם Rambam has a way of reading it that the steps
are shorter, but I read it in a way that at least
gives you a little bit of space, but it's still a little
bit wild that you've got you know nineteen אמות amot length of
these steps in a whole space that's only twenty-two אמות amot wide.
Most of it therefore was like steps leading up. Obviously there's space
to the side of the steps, but when you were in front
of the steps there was very little space between the מזבח and
the steps. Alright? So it was very tight on those steps.
Well, not so much, I mean you had to carry right for
the קטורת, Ketoret, the coals and the קטורת Ketoret and when you
were going in and out, right. But, and it's interesting that you
had all of these larger sort of platforms on the steps, it
wasn't just, you know, you could now remember though, it is actually
right what I forgot to mention is remember who did stand on
the steps were the people stood on it. Who stood on the
steps? כהנים Kohanim for the ברכת כהנים. Birkat Kohanim. Yeah. So that
explains why you want a platform of three, a platform of three,
a platform of four. Maybe they were different, like it's almost like
stadium seating, you know, stadium standing. I'm serious, like there could have
been rows of כהנים, Kohanim, you know, staggered behind each other and
you want them therefore, each of the כהנים Kohanim need a space
to stand and you want them at you know different heights. So
that explains at least why they did it this way for ברכת
כהנים, Birkat Kohanim, but it was huge.
Yeah, the pictures are only three אמות. amot.
Right, so in this picture, right, I mean you see they're sort
of drawing the steps with gaps, which is this idea, but even
the way I read it, others read it in a different way
which leads to twenty-one אמות. amot. Even the way I read it,
which is the ברטנורא, Bartenura, nineteen אמות, amot, it was really almost
very almost no space between the steps and the מזבח, like at
most like you know five feet or something. Okay?
Anyway, it's important to know that those steps were also used as
platforms for the
כהנים. Kohanim. רבי יהודה אומר והעליונה אמה אמה ורובד ה'. Rabbi Yehuda
omer v'ha'elyonah amah amah v'rovad hei. The top one was actually a
platform of five, not a four, so according to this
it
was twenty אמות. amot. Others were 21, but the other מפרשים, mefarshim,
the other
same thing with...
yeah, they said there would be no space, I don't know how
it works, be no space between it and the מזבח. You'd only
have to go up the steps by the side, not by the
front of them or
something. פתחו של אולם...
Pitcho shel Ulam... doesn't really have much of a בין אולם ולמזבח.
bein Ulam velamizbeach.
Well, you
did on the side of the steps. פתחו של אולם, Pitcho shel
Ulam, now the opening of the אולם, Ulam,
right?
And this it's important to look at this picture to realize to
be able to speak about how tall it was. Right? This is
the אולם Ulam and the היכל. Heichal.
It is the closed building in there, that's the inner sanctum. And
now you've gone up these steps and you're at the opening of
the אולם. Ulam. That was very very high. We said that all
the openings were
twenty אמות amot high, which is 30 feet, by ten אמות amot
wide. This is
double. פתחו של אולם גובהו... Pitcho shel Ulam govo... I don't know
what they take this out for... maybe they just let's see what
they change it to... ארבעים ורחבו עשרים. arba’im verochvo esrim. Oh, they
just switch the order.
So it was twenty אמות amot high by...
no, one minute...
yeah that's why they take it out because they don't switch the
order, they switch the... right. It was forty אמות amot high by
twenty אמות amot wide. Okay, so that's 60 feet high the opening,
60 feet, right? By
30 feet
wide. וחמש מלטראות של מילה היו על גביו ve-hamesh malteraot shel mila
hayu al gabav and there were five poles of they say this
is ashwood on the top. Okay, because as if you now this
might be partly decorative, as we'll see their staggering sizes. It might
also be that if you remember it says that they suspended a
curtain. This does not have a door, it had a curtain. Also
cause to make a door 60 feet high is going to be
a pretty big challenge. So they had a curtain, so maybe they
used it partly to suspend the curtain. Okay. So על גביו al
gabav is what? On top? On top of the opening, on top
of the frame of the opening. Okay? Now but it could have
just been a decorative thing that you put on top of an
opening. Now התחתונה עודפת על הפתח אמה ha-tachtona odefet al ha-petach ama
the lowest of these poles it went beyond the opening by an
אמה, ama, אמה מזה ואמה מזה. ama mizeh ve-ama mizeh. So if
the opening was twenty אמות, amot, this was
twenty-two אמות. amot. ושלמעלה ממנה עודפת עליה אמה מזה ואמה מזה. ve-shelimala
mimena odefet aleha ama mizeh ve-ama mizeh. The next one right? It
was sort of like pyramidal
whatever. Anyway the next one was an אמה ama longer than the
one below it on each
side. ועוד למעלה ממנה עודפת עליה אמה מזה ואמה מזה. ve-od lemala
mimena odefet aleha ama mizeh ve-ama mizeh. נמצאת העליונה שלשים אמה. nimtzet
ha-elyona sheloshim ama. So if there were five of them and you
started with the first one being
twenty-two, so it's 22, 24, 26, 28, 30. So the top one
העליונה ל' אמה ha-elyona lamed ama was thirty אמות. amot. So they
had like you know again these like poles of ashwood which made
this nice little triangular shape
on top of the door frame. If you take a look at
the picture you can sort of see I think that they try
to replicate it there. They've got a little something that looks like
a series of lines right on top of the door frame
there. Okay. ונדבך של אבנים היה בין כל אחת ואחת. ve-nidbach shel
avanim haya bein kol achat ve-achat. And there was a row of
bricks between each one of these poles. Okay, so that was the
nice decoration that they had on top and as I said I'm
totally speculating that maybe the poles were also used to suspend the
curtain, but maybe not because probably you suspend the curtain within the
frame not from on top of the frame. All right. ח'. Chet.
Oh I...
Yeah. It's interesting that they're using lintels and not arches.
Yes, so we actually had mentioned that. So that's a good point.
We actually had mentioned it explicitly in a previous משנה Mishnah, that
all of the frames were lintels with one exception which was an
arch. Right? טדי Tadi I think was the one exception, I forget
what... yeah I was wondering about that too because you would have
thought especially since it was you know especially once הורדוס Hordos got
involved that they
would have done much more with an arch. But what I was
also wondering from yesterday is this לשכת העצים, Lishkat ha-Etzim, said it
was open. Why would they make it open? Let's say it rained.
Yeah again you'd have to put stuff under tarps or you'd have
to put them in containers. But you're right it is a little
crazy. It's the same question about the other thing. I mean you
could have stuff in protective containers, but still. Okay.
It's interesting seeing most of the colonnade this
depictions that I see yeah are a
Roman style of column, not a Greek
style.
Aha. Yeah you don't necessarily know how much of this is you
know artist's rendition and how much is based on what they've actually
found
archaeologically. Okay. וכלונסאות של אבנים היו קבועים מכתלו של היכל לכתלו של
אולם. ve-kelonsaot shel avanim hayu kevuim mikotlo shel Heichal lekotlo shel Ulam.
Now they would have to they would have to support the weight
of the walls, they would have supporting beams of stone actually this
says, others say ארז, erez, ארז erez makes more sense, how do
you make beams of stone? So anyway of cedar wood from the
wall of the היכל Heichal. to the wall of the אולם Ulam
כדי שלא יבעט keday shelo yiva’at so that it should not literally
kick, it should not sort of I guess you'd say what's the
word we use buckle. Right. So you actually have a beam that
would go from one wall to the next and I guess they'd
be pushing against each other and against the beam and somehow it
would somebody who knows architecture or whatever. physics better than me I'm
sure could explain that.
Okay. ושרשרות של זהב היו קבועים בתקרת האולם. V'sharsherot shel zahav hayu
kevu'im b'tikrat ha'ulam. Now they would have golden chains on the ceiling
of the אולם Ulam sixty feet up שבהן פרחי כהונה עולים ורואים
את העטרות. shebahen pirchei kehuna olim v'ro'im et ha'atarot. I have no
idea. You see the ropes here? They're climbing chains, golden chains. You
know, they need to get some exercise. It was like a climbing
wall. No,
I'm being irreverent. No, it says that they would climb it. Why?
So that they would climb up these golden chains so that they
could see the crowns. What
crowns? שנאמר והעטרות תהיה לחלם ולטוביה ולידעיה ולחן בן צפניה לזכרון בהיכל
ה'. She'ne'emar v'ha'atarot tihye l'Chelem ul'Tuviya ul'Yeda'aya ul'Chen ben Tzefanya l'zikaron b'Heichal
Hashem. The crowns should be for these various כהנים Kohanim or the
groups of כהנים Kohanim as a remembrance in the היכל. Heichal. So
it is not exactly clear what these crowns were and how you
could exactly see them by climbing up to the top. What? Is
it a רמב"ם? Rambam? You can take a look. It is רמב"ם
Rambam
ד' ח'. Dalet Chet. What?
Gold is a very weak metal.
Yeah, these things have got to be, you always mentioned that, these
things have got to be some type of a gold alloy. Okay.
I mean the only thing it says זהב טהור zahav tahor is
the שולחן. shulchan.
Yeah, these chains were inside
the אולם Ulam before you got to the היכל Heichal behind the
פרוכת.
parochet. No, no, no, no, no.
We're in the אולם Ulam here. This space here before you get
to the היכל. Heichal The היכל, Heichal not the קודש קדשים, Kodesh
Kadashim, the היכל Heichal, where there's the שולחן shulchan and the מנורה.
menorah. You're in the אולם, Ulam, this ante-chamber. But
wait,
was there a פרוכת? parochet? Yeah, there was a curtain in front
of the אולם. Ulam. After you went up the steps, you went
through a curtain. Now there's going to be a door facing you
before you get into the היכל. Heichal. We're going to talk about
that door in a minute. And these chains were in this space
before the door of the היכל Heichal. hanging from the ceiling. You
would climb up and I'm not sure how you could see anything
because there was a wall. So I'm not exactly sure what these
gold crowns were and what exactly you were seeing.
There was a roof or no covering on the אולם?
Ulam? There was a roof. This whole אולם Ulam and the היכל
Heichal. were roofed. Yes, okay. So, okay. Where
were we? Now, and then the last part which we read
before, וגפן של זהב הייתה עומדת על פתחו של היכל. V'gefen shel
zahav hayta omedet al pitcho shel Heichal. They also had an ornamentation
of a gold, you know, vine over the top, around the side
and the top of the opening of the היכל. Heichal ומודלה על
גבי כלונסות, U'mudla al gabei kelonsot, and it was suspended by like
a type of a lattice work. כל מי שהתנדב עלה או גרגיר
או אשכול, Kol mi she'hitnadev aleh o gargir o eshkol, you could
donate a leaf
or a grape or a cluster, a golden one. מביא ותולה בה,
Mevi v'toleh bah, you would bring and you would suspend it. It
sounds like you would get to actually go in yourself and suspend
it. I guess if you're giving a gold leaf, you can go
in and suspend it. אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק. Amar Rabbi Eleazar
berabi Tzadok.
Yeah,
but only כהנים. Kohanim. Well,
you're not actually going into, you're not going into the היכל. Heichal
Could you give me that piece over there? No, no, no, the
one with the text on it. Yeah. You're not going into the
היכל, Heichal you're only going into the אולם. Ulam. Since you have
to be ראוי לביאה ra'ui l'via to
do the עבודה. avoda.
Yeah, but that's the היכל. Heichal You're only going into the אולם.
Ulam. So you can't be בעלי מומין ba'alei mumin or פרועי ראש.
pru'ei rosh. I wonder, but yeah, you do get the sense that
if you're not a כהן, Kohen, you cannot go into any other
part other than the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim. Meaning these כהנים Kohanim
were the ones climbing these. Yeah, I know, I know. I will
say that by the way, it's you do get the sense that
if you're a non-כהן, Kohen, you could only, yesterday we read in
משנת כלים Mishnat Keilim that if you're a non-כהן Kohen and you
need to, you can go into the עזרת כהנים, Ezrat Kohanim, but
that was the space up to the מזבח. You do get the
sense that if you're not a כהן, Kohen, you can't go into
the other space, but I will say that I saw yesterday the
תפארת ישראל, Tiferet Yisrael, a classic commentator on the משנה, mishnah. says
that for example, there's a famous phrasing that like when the רגלים,
that by the time it was
קריאת הגבר, keriat hagever, the עזרה Azara was ממלא כולם ישראל, memale
kulam Yisrael, filled with Jews. He said that doesn't mean עזרת נשים
Ezrat Nashim and it doesn't mean עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, he means
literally the entire עזרה. Azara. Wow. So he actually thinks that there
were times that they would let ישראל Yisrael in all parts of
the עזרה, Azara, which is pretty amazing. But this sounds like it
too. It sounds like anybody would go and hang it up. Well,
it kind of makes sense, right?
You know, they used to show the שולחן shulchan to people, like
look how it's...
Yeah, but that could be... Yeah, but if you bring it out
and you're standing here, you could see too, I guess. Yeah, but
you could see if they're bringing it here, you could see.
No, but on החגים, hechagim, see it nice and hot and...
Synagogues do all kinds of things for money.
All
right. אמר רבי אלעזר ברבי צדוק מעשה היה ונמנו עליה שלוש מאות
כהנים לפנותה. Amar Rabbi Eleazar berabi Tzadok ma'aseh haya v'nimnu aleha shlosh
me'ot kohanim l'fanota. Once they needed three hundred כהנים Kohanim to clean,
to remove all of the gold for, you know, so that they
could sell it or whatever, and as we said, that was an
exaggeration. Okay. Let's go.
We have a few more minutes. Let's start the next משנה. Did
all the people donate? Yes, exactly. Let's go. We're coming to the,
we're coming up to the home stretch, wrapping it all up. פתחו
של היכל, Pitcho shel Heichal, top of ל"ו ע"א. Lamed Vav Amud
Aleph. The opening of the היכל. Heichal גובהו עשרים אמה ורוחבו עשר
אמה. Govho esrim ama v'rochvo eser ama. So we did the opening
of the אולם, Ulam, now the opening of the היכל. So this
is the normal sized opening, twenty אמות amot by
ten, ורוחבו עשר. v'rochvo eser. And it had four
doors, שתים בפנים ושתים בחוץ. shtayim bifnim ve-shtayim bachutz. Now the width
of the actual wall itself was a huge thick wall, was six
אמות. amos. It was like ten feet width of a wall. Imagine
that? Really thick wall, okay, six אמות. amos. So they had a
six-amah thick wall. Remember we talked yesterday, we're gonna talk again, about
how when they had to open the היכל they went through like
a tunnel until they got to the other side. That tunnel to
get into the inside of the היכל wasn't a tunnel, it was
the thickness of the wall, was six אמות. amos. Okay, so, and
the opening was ten אמות. amos. So what we're going to say
is each opening had two doors. Just imagine this, it's very simple
actually, right? If each opening had two doors and each door was
five אמות, amos, okay, then you open into the width of the
opening and the opening is six אמות, amos, the back of the
doors covers most of the inside of the opening. So the outside
doors, here's the way it's going to work, the outside doors of
the היכל are going to open in. There are two sets of
doors. And the inside doors here are going to open out. Okay,
so I mean all of them sort of open, you know, all
of them are push doors, not pull doors if you're coming from
the outside. So this opens into the width
of the wall, and then you come, and at the end there
are other doors and then you push those open too and they
open
into the
היכל, into the היכל. Okay. So וארבע דלתות היו להם, ve-arba dlatos
hayu lahem, שתים בפנים ושתים בחוץ, shtayim bifnim ve-shtayim bachutz, two on
the inside, two on the outside, שנאמר ושתים דלתות להיכל ולקודש. shene-emar
ushtayim dlatos la-heichal vela-kodesh. Okay, a פסוק from יחזקאל. Yechezkel. החיצונות נפתחות
לתוך הפתח, ha-chitzonos niftachos letoch hapetach, the outer ones open as I
said if you're coming from the outside you push as it were,
they open into
the opening, לכסות עביו של כותל, lechafos ovyo shel kotel, they fill
up the width of the כותל kotel because again almost the whole
width. The space was ten so each door was five, so it
covers most of the width of the
wall. והפנימיות נפתחות לתוך הבית, vehapenimiyos niftachos letoch habayis, and the inner
ones open into the house, לכסות אחר הדלתות, lechafos achar hadlatos, and
then when they open the back of those doors basically you know
are against that section of the wall of the היכל. Right? I
mean you just open it into the width so they're against the
wall of the היכל. They go
flat. Right. Okay. So שכל הבית טוח בזהב, shekol habayis tuach bezahav,
the entire
בית which is the היכל was
plastered, but what would be the word, laid with
gold, חוץ מאחור הדלתות. chutz me-achar hadlatos. The one thing they did
not lay with gold was the space behind the doors, because when
the doors are open, right, you can't see the wall behind them
and the doors are gold. So who needs the walls to be
gold if the doors are covering that section of the walls? I
guess the point is the only person who would see the exposed
walls would be the כהן kohen that would go in the first
thing in order to open the doors. He would see the exposed
walls. But once the doors were opened, they covered that section so
they did not bother to actually cover the walls themselves with
gold. רבי יהודה אומר בתוך הפתח היו עומדות. Rabbi Yehuda omer betoch
hapetach hayu omados. Actually he says both doors would open into the
inside of the thickness of the wall. Now how could you do
that? The doors were five אמות amos and the thickness was six.
So how can this open inside and this open inside? They sort
of, you know, bang up against each other. So he says, here's
his
answer, היו עומדות וכמין אסטרמיטא היו. hayu omados u-kemin ister-mita hayu. They
were sort of like an אסטרמיטא ister-mita which people say basically is
like a what do they call like a Chinese door like a
Chinese, you know, it's a folding door. Meaning the door itself is
hinged. Right. That's what I was gonna say. The door itself is
hinged. So you have the door was five אמות, amos, but it's
tiered, but it's two sections on a hinge. So when you open
it into the inside, you can fold it up like that. Okay,
a bi-fold door. So therefore each door only took up two and
a half אמות amos inside the thickness of the wall. So they
could both open to the inside.
Was one of the first set of doors closed
before you opened the inner set?
Yeah, we're gonna talk about the order that they got opened in
a minute. So let's first finish
this. ונכפלות לאחוריהן, venifalos leachoreihen, and they would fold back, you know,
to behind them. Meaning they'd fold back on themselves. אלו שתי אמות
ומחצה ואלו שתי אמות ומחצה. elu shtei amos u-mechtza ve-elu shtei amos
u-mechtza. So a five-amah door became two and a half אמות. amos.
So they were both able to open to the inside of the
wall. חצי אמה מזוזה מכאן וחצי אמה מזוזה מכאן. chatzi amah mezuza
mikan ve-chatzi amah mezuza mikan. Now the whole thickness was six, but
you needed at least a half an אמה amah on each side
for the actual, you know, hinge, for the actual
מזוזה. mezuza. Okay. שנאמר ושתים דלתות לדלתות, shene-emar ushtayim dlatos ladlatos, that
the two doors for each
door, שתים מוסבות דלתות, shtayim musabos dlatos, דלתות שתים לדלת אחת ושתי
דלתות לאחרת. dlatos shtayim ladelet achas ushtei dlatos la-acheres. Anyway, two doors
they would be מוסבות, musabos, they would be hinged, and they would
be two doors for each door. So each door would be
essentially two sections would be hinged and therefore you could open them
both to the inside. And now we're going to read how they
would open them, and this also goes back
to תמיד. Tamid. ושני פשפשין היו לו לשער הגדול. ushne pishpishin hayu
lo lasha'ar hagadol. There were two like chambers for the major gate.
And I think when I read this in תמיד. I imagined that
it was a little door inside of a large one, but now
that we're already describing that these doors are themselves relatively small, I
mean not small whatever anyway, but it's not one big gate door,
most I think the better explanation and the way they have it
in this picture if you look, I'll just use this, is that
it was not actually a little section in the door itself but
to the side of the door. So here are the double doors
and here are these little side chambers cut into the wall, these
crawlspaces or whatever they are cut into the wall, and they're going
to let you get access into the היכל without going through the
door. Okay?
אחד בצפון ואחד בדרום, Echad batzafon v'echad badarom, one in the north
and one in the south. שבדרום לא נכנס אדם בו מעולם, Shebadarom
lo nichnas adam bo mei'olam, the south nobody ever went into. ועליו
הוא מפורש על ידי יחזקאל, V'alav hu mforash al yedei Yechezkel, and
regarding it, it is explained through Ezekiel, שנאמר, Shene'emar, as it is
said, ויאמר ה' אלי השער הזה סגור יהיה לא יפתח ואיש לא
יבוא בו כי ה' אלוהי ישראל בא בו. Vayomer Hashem elay hasha'ar
hazeh sagur yihiyeh lo yipateiach v'ish lo yavo vo ki Hashem Elokei
Yisrael ba vo. This one will be sealed, nobody will go, this
is where God goes as we said. That's a little strange, you
know, what exactly is he trying to communicate? But maybe it's as
we said. That is the little thing on the picture, yeah, it
is, it's the one that says ס"ג Samech Gimmel
here. It's this. It's the one on the south I think they
said, right? Yeah, so this one. So this little, like this? This.
This little thing would get you into a chamber next to the
היכל but this door would be always locked. That's for God? Yeah,
exactly. And this one would be the way you would get in
and open up the giant door. Well, the whole point is it's
locked to show that God doesn't need a door. Okay, we have
to finish. Okay, כי השער, Ki hasha'ar, okay, ויהי סגור. V'yehi sagur.
נטל את המפתח. Natal es hamafteiach. Now of course it's no good
if you have locked doors if your crawlway into the doors is
open. So that was also locked. So he would take the key,
right? Remember the keys that were stored in the בית המוקד? Beis
HaMoked? This is what you do and you'd open it
up. ופתח את הפשפש. U'pasach es hapishpish. You'd open up this little
escape way, the
chamber. ונכנס להתא. V'nichnas lahata. And you went from there into, through
this crawl space, into this actual chamber in the wall, crawlway? Whatever,
I don't know what it is. ומהתא להיכל. U'meihata l'heichal. And from
there there was an exit into the היכל itself. And now you
are in the inside of the היכל and you could open the
doors. And that's how the doors would be
opened. רבי יהודה אומר בתוך עוביו של כותל היה מהלך עד שנמצא
עומד בין שני השערים. Rebbi Yehuda omer besoch ovyo shel koseil haya
meihaleich ad shenimtza omeid bein shnei hasha'arim. So he says that rather
than going like this and going and now you're facing both doors,
it sounds like he said you would crawl inside a crawl space
and you'd come out between the two doors. You'd actually be between
the front and the back
door. ופתח את החיצונה מבפנים ואת הפנימית מבחוץ. U'pasach es hachitzonah mibifnim
v'es hapnimis mibachutz. So this is all according to רבי יהודה. Rebbi
Yehuda. He says if you're standing between the two doors, so then
you open, you know, the outer ones inside and the inner ones
outside, assuming again we're going like that, you're standing between the two
doors. But assuming you get behind the doors, obviously you first open
the inner one and then you walk through the space and you
open the outer one. Alright, to be wrapped up tomorrow.